Guide to the Donald J. Schofield Papers 1941-2016 (bulk 1941-1952)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Donald J. Schofield Papers
1941-2016 (Bulk 1941-1952)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 927
Schofield, Donald J., 1921-1994
0.5 linear feet
This collection concerns the life and career of Donald J. Schofield. The collection includes materials of study from the University of Montana, records of employment and military activities, and ephemera from the Forestry Club at the University of Montana.
Biographical Note
Donald J. Schofield was born December 19, 1921 in West Falls Church, Virginia. He attended Michigan State College from 1940 to 1941. In the summer of 1941, he served with the U.S. Forest Service fire crew stationed at Ninemile Camp Menard in Western Montana (then Nine Mile) immediately after its transition from the Civilian Conservation Corps to the U.S. Forest Service. During World War II, Schofield served in the 8th U.S. Army Air Corps, in the 392nd Bombardment Group, as a navigator on the B-24 Liberator Bombers. He was stationed in England and flew missions to Germany and earned numerous awards and citations for his service.
After World War II, Donald Schofield attended the University of Montana (then Montana State University) School of Forestry starting in the year 1946 and graduating with a Bachelor of Science degree in Forestry in 1948. He was actively involved in the Forestry Club, the Forestry Kaimin, and the Forester's Ball, serving as the Chief Push for the 31st Forester's Ball in 1948. After graduating from the University of Montana, Schofield was employed by the U.S. Department of the Interior Bureau of Land Management from 1948 to 1976. He then served on the Board of Commissioners for Jackson County in Oregon from 1978 to 1980. Donald Schofield died January 23, 1994 in Ashland, Oregon.
The Donald J. Schofield collection includes materials and documents from his life, education, and employment. Included in this collection are various military records dating to World War II and his position as a navigator in the Army Air Corps. The majority of the materials in this collection reflect his studies and careers in the field of forestry. Included are documents, ephemera, and records from his time at the University of Montana (then Montana State University) and his career prior to and after the completion of his forestry degree. Also included is a biography of Schofield's military career written by his daughter in 2016.
Folders in this collection are arranged chronologically.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This collection was held by Donald Schofield's son prior to tranfer to Archives and Special Collections.
This collection was donated to the University of Montana by Gordon Schofield in 2019.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Schofield, Donald J., 1921-1994--Archives
United States. Forest Service--Officials and employees; United States. Bureau of Land Management--Officials and employees; United States. Army Air Forces.$bBombardment Group (H), 392nd; Montana State University (Missoula, Mont.)--History--20th century
Nine Mile (Missoula County, Mont.)--History--20th century
World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American; Airmen--United States--Biography; Forests and forestry--Montana
Student Life; Military; Montana
- Nine Mile Notes, 1941; Nine Mile Notes is a newsletter published by the men who worked at Nine Mile. (Box-folder 1/1)
- Nine Mile Photographs, 1941 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Early Employment Records, 1942-1957 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Military Records, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Montana State University Records, 1945-1948; Records include Student handbook, commencement programs, and alumni association cards. (Box-folder 1/5)
- Lecture Notebooks, 1946, 1948 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Forestry Club, Circa 1946-1948; Materials include Code of Ethics, Forestry Song Book, and membership cards (Box-folder 1/7)
- Forester's Ball, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Forester's Ball Program, 1946 (Box 2)
- Forestry Photographs, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Bureau of Land Management, 1976 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Montana Druids, 1981 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Military Biography of D. Schofield, 2016; Written by Anne Schofield (Daughter of Donald Schofield) (Box-folder 1/12)